Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today we
have a new lesson in our series about
interviewing for a new job.
This is of course at the elementary level.
That's right so this is part four of our
interview series. Remember we are taking a
look each week at giving you
tips and also the proper language
for when you have an interview in
English and on this occasion we're going to
talk about our work experience. Okay
you remember we talked a little bit about
educational experience and educational
background. Well today is all about your
last couple of jobs. Alright so I think
we should just listen to the dialogue
for the first time and we'll be
back in a bit with language takeaway.
Right Rebecca. Now I see that after
graduating from university your first job was
for a local paper in York called The
York Herald. Actually I started with them
as an intern. I was really keen on
getting some experience and journalism
and this seemed like a good first step.
Certainly and after your internship
they seemed impressed and offered me
a position as a junior local news reporter.
I ended up staying two years there
actually. I was in charge of the sports
news section of the newspaper. I really
enjoyed it there and it really helped me
build my skills. Yes I see but you
decided to leave them in 2006 right?
Yes that's right my husband and I moved
to London and so I managed to find a
position with a national newspaper based
in London. It's a London weekly right?
Yes in some ways it was a
step down from my previous job
but it did offer me much
better prospects for the future.
Alright we're back so now we've picked out
a couple of key words and we're going to
take a look at those now
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So Marco a lot of people don't start out
as a professional with a job. They
have something else first what is this?
That's right a very
popular way to begin your
work experience. You become
an intern or you work as an intern.
Okay so the name of the job we
could say is intern. I'm an intern or he's
an intern at my company. Exactly so
usually interns work at a company. Usually
they're not paid and or if they are it's a
very very little pay and the purpose of an
internship or to work as an intern is
to gain experience. That's right so it's
basically like a study opportunity for a
job that you know you want. I could be an
intern at a media
company and I could learn
all about media but
it's not really a full job.
Exactly and usually it
serves as an opportunity
to maybe continue working
at that company in the
full-time job. So you
become an intern and the
noun or the what you are
doing is called an internship.
So I'm an intern but what
I have is an internship.
Right it's like
saying I have a job.
I have an internship but
I am an intern. Exactly.
Alright so we've covered
those two words now.
Let's move on to when
she's describing her work
experience in the York
Herald and she described it
as a very good first
step. Okay so a first step
you think about your foot
your step you're moving
it means the very first
thing you do when you're
heading in some direction.
Right and professionally
I guess your first steps are
maybe becoming an intern.
Right or you could
say my first step was
working in the mail room
at this big movie studio
but later I became you
know famous movie producer.
Exactly so that's kind
of like the way that
you begin your professional
life. And well then
they started talking
about the newspapers and
actually Rebecca was
offered a position as a junior
local news reporter.
Okay so junior means
usually lower ranking
or not not experienced
someone who is just
starting out and of course after
junior we have senior.
So a senior news reporter
is someone who's worked for
many many years as a reporter.
Usually I guess a
junior news reporter
would like make less money
than a senior news reporter.
Exactly you could also
say junior executive or
senior executive. Junior
manager. These are ways
of describing length
of experience and in this
case she's junior but
what kind of job does
she have while she is a
news reporter for local issues.
Okay so she's a local
news reporter now
what exactly does that
mean if you're a local
news reporter or for
local issues. Well if I live
in Chicago and I'm a
local news reporter I only
write or report the
news about Chicago.
It's a way of describing
the things in my area.
So it's the opposite of our next
phrase national news reporter.
Okay so if you are a
national news reporter
or a national manager of
maybe a company then that
means that you oversee
things in the whole country.
That's right so local is
my city or my county but
in the case of national
we're talking about the
whole country nation
national. So national is an
adjective but we could
even go further than this.
What if I am a reporter and I
talk about foreign countries.
I talk about France and South Africa and
even Iceland. Then I guess you would be an
international news reporter.
Exactly and I guess also
at the executive level you
can have an international
marketing manager right.
That's right international
marketing manager not
national marketing manager.
These are very important ways to divide
work to say he is the international manager.
Here's the national manager.
This tells you the kind of the
size of this person's
job. Exactly okay so now
more or less you know how
these jobs can be divided
junior, senior,
national, local etc.
So I think we should go back
to the dialogue. Let's listen to
this dialogue again
and we'll be back in a bit.
Right Rebecca now I see
that after graduating from
university your first
job was for a local paper
in York called The York
Herald. Actually I started
with them as an intern. I
was really keen on getting
some experience in
journalism and this seemed
like a good first step.
Certainly and after your
internship they seemed
impressed and offered me a
position as a junior
local news reporter.
I ended up staying
two years there actually.
I was in charge of the sports
news section of the newspaper.
I really enjoyed it there
and it really helped
me build my skills. Yes
I see but you decided
to leave them in 2006
right? Yes that's right my
husband and I moved to
London and so I managed to
find a position with a national
newspaper based in London.
It's a London weekly right?
Yes in some ways it was a step
down from my previous job but it
did offer me much better
prospects for the future.
All right so now let's
start with a couple of
phrases and phrasal
verbs on fluency builder.
Fluency Builder. Okay in
today's dialogue we heard
a lot of really wonderful
phrases Marco.
Some of them are ways of making
your experiences sound better.
More professional
even. For example this
first one sorry Rebecca's
talking about her first job
in New York and she
says I was in charge of the
sports news section.
Okay so that phrase I was in
charge of or to be in charge
of what is this described?
This describes responsibility.
Basically she's saying I was
responsible for or I had to
manage the sports news
section. She's taking credit
for this this job
that was important.
Okay so this is a key phrase
because this is the typical
phrase that you use to
describe your responsibilities
or to describe what
you did in your previous
job position or your
previous job. Sorry I could
ask you when you were in
marketing what were you in charge of?
Right and then
you say well I was in
charge of and then you
explain your responsibilities
or what you did. I was
in charge of our national
accounts or I was in
charge of the local news.
Exactly so this is a very
simple phrase just remember
it. I was in charge of
and then you can start
explaining what were your
responsibilities what you
did in your previous job.
All right moving on now
towards the end of that
paragraph Rebecca says that
well being in charge of
the sports news section
was really fun and it really
helped her build my skills.
It really helped
me build my skills.
So to build your skills
or in this case I build
my skills means that I
I have some skills but
maybe they're not really
developed. Maybe you know
I just finished college I
want more experience
well in that time during
my first job I build my skills.
I become better at writing or making
having interviews things like that.
Exactly so when you build
your skills you can improve your
abilities or you gain
more experience.
And another interesting phrase
coming up here when Rebecca
talked about moving to
London with her husband
she said I managed
to find a position with a
national newspaper. Okay so I managed to
or you could say to manage to do something.
This is a really interesting
phrase because it's another way
of saying to be able to or
to succeed at something.
Okay so don't confuse it with a
manager or to manage people.
That is also
correct to obviously
it exists but to manage to do something is
to as you said to be able to do something.
Right so for example I
was running really late
yesterday and I had a ticket
for a train at five o'clock.
I thought I would miss the train but I
managed to get to the train on time.
That means I was able to
get on the train on time.
Exactly okay so you managed
to find a job. I managed to get
to the train on time. I
was able to. All right and
towards the end Rebecca
talked about her job at
the London weekly and
she described it as a step
down for my previous
job. Okay so it's a good
thing or a bad thing
Marco. To be a step down in
something is a bad thing it's
to reduce in level or to decrease.
Okay so basically
she's saying listen
I had this really great
job in New York and I took
a new job in London
and the new job it wasn't
as good in many ways
because maybe she had less
responsibility or
maybe it paid less.
So this is a way of saying it
wasn't as good as my last job.
Okay so her new job
but was a step down from
her previous job. You
could say I think his new
girlfriend's a bit of a step
down if you know what I mean.
Exactly so usually
you're comparing right
you're making a comparison
between something from
the past to now. Exactly.
Okay so a step down.
Why don't we go back
and listen to the dialogue
for the very last time
and we'll be back to talk
to you in a bit. Right
Rebecca now I see that
after graduating from
University your first job was
for a local paper in York
called The York Herald.
Actually I started
with them as an intern
I was really keen on
getting some experience in
journalism and this
seemed like a good first step.
Certainly and after your
internship they seemed
impressed and offered
me a position as a junior
local news reporter. I ended up
staying two years there actually.
I was in charge of the sports news
section of the newspaper. I really enjoyed
it there and it really
helped me build my skills.
Yes I see but you decided
to leave them in 2006 right?
Yes that's right my
husband and I moved to
London and so I managed to find a position
with a national newspaper based in London.
It's a London weekly
right? Yes in some ways
it was a step down from
my previous job but it
did offer me much better
prospects for the future.
All right so talking
about internships and
interns it seems that
usually they get it's not
very exciting to become
an intern because it
ends up that the office
people just make you
make coffee or or
copies and stuff like that.
You're not really gaining
much work experience.
That is the reputation in the United States
for internships so basically when you
agree to do an internship
sometimes you have
to apply to do an internship.
It's a very long process.
You end up like you
say making coffee for
people or photocopying reports
and this is really boring work.
Right I think yeah that that is the reputation
that many places have like you say in
the United States but
also I don't know I guess
it does seem in a way
the only opportunity in
order to be able to get into
an industry or a company.
Maybe it's a really good
company like I don't
know like a like proctoring
gamble and how else
are you going to be able to get
in there with no job experience?
Well that's right
and a lot of people
know that an internship
doesn't really give you
work experience but
they'd still think that it
gives you some edge or
some advantage when you're
looking for jobs later
because if I write down
on my my resume we were
talking earlier about resumes.
If I write down on my resume that I
was an intern at proctoring gamble.
Wow that's really impressive.
Right it looks good.
Alright so this is an
interesting topic. Let us know if
you were ever an intern.
Maybe you started out
as an internship or maybe
you're doing one now.
Was it better than we
say? Did you do anything
else other than making
coffee? We really hope so
and that we we look
forward to hearing about
your experiences. Alright
we'll see everyone at
EnglishPod.com and until next time bye bye.